Guide to the Center for Death Penalty Litigation Records, 1953-2020; 1953-ongoing and undated RL.00199
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Center for Death Penalty Litigation records
1953-2020 and undated; 1953-ongoing
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Center for Death Penalty Litigation
RL.00199
66 Linear Feet
The Center for Death Penalty Litigation is a non-profit law firm that represents inmates on North Carolina's death row. Its work often involves the investigation of racism and the judicial process, and the treatment of people with mental disabilities charged with crimes in North Carolina. Collection contains Center for Death Penalty Litigation case files dating from 1953-2020 for seventeen inmates on North Carolina's death row during the same period: Robert Bacon Jr., David Junior Brown, Frederick Camacho, Willie Ervin Fisher, George Earl Goode Jr., Harvey Lee Green Jr., Zane Hill, David Earl Huffstetler, Joseph Timothy Keel (the largest case file at 26 boxes), Gary Wayne Long, James Lewis Martin Jr., Elton Ozell McLaughlin, Phillip Thomas Robbins Jr., Steve Van McHone, Jimmy McNeill, Clinton Cebert Smith, and Norris Carlton Taylor, as well as limited files on other inmates. Case files typically include transcripts, affidavits, attorney notes, clemency requests, petitions, pleadings, photographs, correspondence, motions, Department of Corrections documents, Resource Center files, investigative files, audiovisual materials, and some electronic records.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Center for Death Penalty Litigation Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2007-2009.
Collection Overview
The records of the Center for Death Penalty Litigation (CDPL) span the years 1953-2020, and contain the Center's case files for seventeen inmates on North Carolina's death row during the same period: Robert Bacon Jr., David Junior Brown, Frederick Camacho, Willie Ervin Fisher, George Earl Goode Jr., Harvey Lee Green Jr., Zane Hill, David Earl Huffstetler, Joseph Timothy Keel (the largest case file at 26 boxes), Gary Wayne Long, James Lewis Martin Jr., Elton Ozell McLaughlin, Phillip Thomas Robbins Jr., Steve Van McHone, Jimmy McNeill, Clinton Cebert Smith, and Norris Carlton Taylor, as well as limited files on other inmates and web content from the organization. The Center for Death Penalty Litigation's work often involves the investigation of racism and the judicial process, and the treatment of people with mental disabilities charged with crimes in North Carolina.[Note: materials in this collection may use outdated terms such as "mentally retarded" to refer to people with mental disabilities.] Case files typically include some combination of transcripts, affidavits, attorney notes, clemency requests, petitions, pleadings, correspondence, motions, investigative files, Department of Corrections documents, photographs, audiovisual materials, Resource Center files, and in some cases, electronic files. The case files are arranged in alphabetical order by the defendant's last name. The Web Series consists of crawls of the Center for Death Penalty Litigation website. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Related Materials
Robert P. Mosteller papers, 1978-2002, Law professor at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Former president of the North Carolina Center for Death Penalty Litigation. Legal files, transcripts, and motions from the case of John Wesley Oliver, a former death row inmate in North Carolina. Includes materials from his initial trial with co-defendant George Moore and subsequent appeals in North Carolina's court system.
Sentences (Criminal procedure) -- North Carolina; Videocassettes; People with mental disabilities and crime -- North Carolina; Racism -- North Carolina; Criminal courts -- North Carolina; Capital punishment -- North Carolina -- Cases; Capital punishment -- Law and legislation -- United States; North Carolina. Judicial Dept; Murder -- Law and legislation -- North Carolina; Justice, Administration of -- North Carolina; Insanity (Law) -- North Carolina; Keel, Joseph Timothy; Long, Gary Wayne; Martin, James Lewis; McLaughlin, Elton Ozell; Green, Harvey Lee; Hill, Zane; Huffstetler, David Earl; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Camacho, Frederick; Center for Death Penalty Litigation; Fisher, Willie Ervin; Bacon, Robert, Jr; Brown, David Junior; Taylor, Norris Carlton; Robbins, Phillip Thomas; Van McHone, Steve; Goode, George Earl, Jr.; McNeill, Jimmy, 1953-; Smith, Clinton Cebert, 1960-
- Case Files Series, 1969-2006, 115 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Case files are arranged in alphabetical order by defendant's last name: Robert Bacon Jr., David Junior Brown, Frederick Camacho, Willie Ervin Fisher, Harvey Lee Green Jr., Zane Hill, David Earl Huffstetler, Joseph Timothy Keel (the largest case file at 26 boxes), Gary Wayne Long, James Lewis Martin Jr., Elton Ozell McLaughlin, and Phillip Thomas Robbins Jr.. They typically include some combination of transcripts, affidavits, attorney notes, investigative files, clemency requests, audiovisual materials, petitions, pleadings, testimony (including medical, legal, and eyewitness), correspondence, motions, photographs, Resource Center files, and some electronic records. Each individual's case history is described at beginning of the corresponding file grouping. The majority of the case files consist of 5-9 boxes of materials. The smallest case files at two boxes each are for Camacho and Robbins; the largest are those of Keel and McLaughlin, at 26 and 20 boxes respectively. Folder titles below are original titles as supplied by CDPL staff, and the original order of the files within each case group has been retained. The contents of electronic files have been migrated to a library server; please contact Research Services to use this material.
  [Original recordings are closed to research. Use copies must be made before contents can be accessed.]
  Legal Terms and Definitions
  Affidavit: any written document in which the signer swears under oath before a notary public or someone authorized to take oaths (like a County Clerk), that the statements in the document are true.
  Appellant: the party who appeals a trial court decision he/she/it has lost.
  Appellee: in some jurisdictions the name used for the party who has won at the trial court level, but the loser (appellant) has appealed the decision to a higher court. Thus the appellee has to file a response to the legal brief filed by the appellant. In many jurisdictions the appellee is called the "respondent."
  Certiorari: a writ (order) of a higher court to a lower court to send all the documents in a case to it so the higher court can review the lower court's decision. Certiorari is most commonly used by the U.S. Supreme Court, which is selective about which cases it will hear on appeal.
  En banc: signifies a decision by the full court of all the appeals judges in jurisdictions where there is more than one three- or four-judge panel. The larger number sit in judgment when the court feels there is a particularly significant issue at stake or when requested by one or both parties to the case and agreed to by the court.
  Habeas corpus: writ (court order) which directs the law enforcement officials (prison administrators, police or sheriff) who have custody of a prisoner to appear in court with the prisoner to help the judge determine whether the prisoner is lawfully in prison or jail.
  In forma pauperis: referring to a party to a lawsuit who gets filing fees waived by filing a declaration of lack of funds (has no money to pay).
  Mandamus: a writ (more modernly called a "writ of mandate") which orders a public agency or governmental body to perform an act required by law when it has neglected or refused to do so.
  Motion of appropriate relief: relief is a generic term for all types of benefits which an order or judgment of court can give a party to a lawsuit, including money award, injunction, return of property, property title, alimony and dozens of other possibilities.
  Motion of summary judgment: a written request for a judgment in the moving party's favor before a lawsuit goes to trial and based on testimony recorded outside court, affidavits (declarations under penalty of perjury), depositions, admissions of fact and/or answers to written interrogatories, claiming that all factual and legal issues can be decided in the moving party's favor.
  Subpoena: a court order requiring a witness to bring documents in the possession or under the control of the witness to a certain place at a certain time. This subpena must be served personally on the person subpenaed. It is a common way to obtain potentially useful evidence, such as documents and business records, in the possession of a third party.
  (Definitions taken from law.com website.)
  - Robert Bacon, Jr., 1987-2003, 12 boxes
    Robert Bacon Jr. and Bonnie Clark were charged with first-degree murder for the killing of Clark's husband. Bacon, an African American male, had been dating and living together with Bonnie Clark, a white female. At trial, Bacon received the death penalty from an all-white jury while Clark was sentenced to life in prison. The jury had discussed Bacon's romantic involvement with a white woman in deciding Bacon's sentencing. In 1999, a federal district court judge held a hearing and ruled that Bacon's lawyers had improperly prepared for his defense. After many hearings and reversals, Bacon's execution was set for October 2001. N.C. Governor Michael Easley granted Bacon clemency on October 5, 2001 and Bacon was sentenced to life in prison. This case file includes videos relating to Bacon's sentencing and clemency plea.
    - Responses to state motions (Box 1)
    - Order for evidentiary hearing - 5/29/1999 (Box 1)
    - Evidentiary hearing transcript - 6/21/1999 (Box 1)
    - Petition's response to motion summary judgment - 2/18/1998 (Box 1)
    - Order granting writ - 9/17/99 (Box 1)
    - Petitioner's letter to N.C. Department of Justice - 10/4/1999 (Box 1)
    - Petitioner's supplementary memo, 5/8/2000 (Box 1)
    - En banc petition, denied 9/26/2000 (Box 1)
    - U.S. Court of Appeals
      - Supplemental brief (Box 1)
      - Answering brief (Box 1)
      - Bacon v. Lee (Box 1)
    - Motions and sentencing documents (Box 1)
    - Interviews
      - Bacon (Box 1)
      - Family (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Interviews, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - State summary judgment denial (Box 2)
    - Petition for writ of habeas corpus (Box 2)
    - Exhibits for writ of habeas corpus (Box 2)
    - Transcripts (Box 2)
    - U.S. Supreme Court files (Box 2)
    - U.S. Court of Appeals, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Race and dealth penalty in N.C. study, 1993-1997 (Box 2)
    - Bacon's Department of Corrections file (Box 2)
    - Mental health records (Box 2)
    - Medical records and social history (Box 2)
    - High school records (Box 2)
    - Prison medical files, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - District attorney's notes (Box 3)
    - Notes, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Defense notes (Box 3)
    - Pecuniary gain (Box 3)
    - Evidence of other trial (Box 3)
    - Filed motions (Box 3)
    - Notes (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Jury acknowledgment (Box 4)
    - Watson motion, letter of 10/23/1990, Merritt and case (Box 4)
    - Testimony (Box 4)
      These files contain testimony of 43 individuals, including witnesses, doctors, family members, and friends.
    - Transcript (1275-1375) (Box 4)
    - Trial summary (Box 4)
    - Transcript summaries - motions, open/close of trial (Box 5)
    - Closing arguments
      - Andrews and Coxe (Box 5)
      - Merritt, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Motions (Box 5)
    - State's evidence, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Jury charge and verdict (Box 5)
    - Trial transcript - volume II (Box 5)
    - Trial transcripts (Box 6)
      - Volume II (Box 6)
      - Volume III, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Volume IV (incomplete), 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 2008-0117-Disk 002 American Radioworks Documentary: Deadly Decisions (Box 6)
    - Correspondence (Box 6)
    - Victim's family (Box 6)
    - Execution date change - 9/11/2001 (Box 6)
    - Minister support for Bacon (Box 7)
    - Motions (Box 7)
    - Fourth Circuit Press (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Newspaper articles (Box 7)
    - Bonnie Clark - possible exhibits (Box 7)
    - Exhibits (Box 7)
    - Jury investigations (Box 7)
    - Black caucus (Box 7)
    - Package to Governor Easley - 5/11/2001 (Box 7)
    - Dissenting juror affidavit (Box 7)
    - Supplemental materials for Gov. (Box 7)
    - Bacon support from Massachusetts legislator (Box 7)
    - Bacon supporter documents, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Clemency (Box 7)
    - International law IACHR, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Supreme Court documents (Box 8)
    - Stay of execution - 5/17/2001 (Box 8)
    - Bonnie Clark - supreme court (Box 8)
    - Bacon I (Box 8)
    - Bacon II (Box 8)
    - Court's decision - 8/30/2000 (Box 8)
    - Motions (Box 8)
    - Mental health documents (Box 8)
    - Petition for clemency (Box 8)
    - Commutation order (Box 8)
    - Support for Bacon, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Press, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - N.C. Supreme Court - Bacon I and Bonnie Clark (Box 8)
    - Testimony
      - Bonnie Clark (Box 8)
    - Testimony files (Box 9)
      These files contain testimony of 23 individuals, including witnesses, doctors, family members, and friends.
    - Opening statements - Andrews and Coxe (Box 9)
    - Supreme Court file, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Office of Appellate Defender files (Box 9)
    - Jury questionnaire (Box 9)
    - Trial transcripts
      - Volume II (Box 9)
      - Volume III (Box 9)
    - Trial transcripts (Box 10)
      - Volume IV (Box 10)
      - Volume V (Box 10)
      - Volume VIII (Box 10)
      - Volume X (Box 10)
    - North Carolina Supreme Court (NCSC)
      - Additional brief (Box 10)
      - Defendant - appellant's brief (Box 10)
      - Submission - 3/7/1989 (Box 10)
      - Bonnie Clark (Box 10)
    - North Carolina v. Bonnie Clark, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Notes on jury selection (Box 11)
    - Closing (Box 11)
    - N.C. Supreme Court - North Carolina v. Robert Bacon, Jr. (Box 11)
    - 2008-0117-Video 001 Bacon Clemency Video Answer Print (Box 12)
    - 2008-0117-Video 002 Bacon Clemency Video, Burncode dub of interview master (Box 12)
    - 2008-0117-Video 003 Bacon Clemency Video, Burncode dub of interview master (Box 12)
    - 2008-0117-Video 004 #2 Sentencing Bacon (Box 12)
  - David Junior Brown, 1980-1999, 11 boxes
    David Junior Brown was convicted of two counts of first degree murder and sentenced to death in 1980. At trial, Brown's lawyers attacked the weaknesses in the State's evidence relating to the police investigation and the time of death. Fourteen years after Brown was sentenced to death, the State disclosed that the prosecutor had hidden evidence of innocence from defense counsel; a witness had seen the victims alive at a time that made it virtually impossible for Brown to have committed the crime. At the point at which the State disclosed the exculpatory evidence, Brown's case was in federal court. The federal courts ruled that Brown could not meet the standard for entitlement to habeas relief, and Brown was executed in November 1999.
    - Discovery files (Box 11)
      - State Bureau of Investigation (SBI) lab work, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - SBI general files, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - SBI personal files (Box 11)
    - Discovery files (Box 13)
      - SBI personal files (Box 13)
      - Brown's supplementary discovery, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - SBI official reports (Box 13)
      - Brown articles (Box 13)
      - Union County documents (Box 13)
    - Union County documents (Box 14)
    - Record on appeal (Box 14)
    - Appendices
      - Appendix to writ of habeas corpus (Box 14)
      - Appendix to state's brief, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Appendices C and D, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Jury investigation (Box 14)
    - Asheville files, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Asheville 8/5/1996 (Box 15)
    - Appendix C and D (Box 15)
    - Original trial transcripts
      - Volumes I-III (Box 15)
      - Volumes IV-V, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Volumes VI-VII (Box 15)
    - Original trial transcripts (Box 16)
      - Volume VIII (Box 16)
      - Volumes VIII-IX (Box 16)
    - SBI files, 5 folders (Box 16)
    - SBI files (Box 17)
    - Discovery material from district attorney, 4/11/1995, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Investigation photos, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Crime scene photos, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Evidence
      - Information (Box 17)
      - Manuals, photos, and reports (Box 17)
    - Evidence - documents and photos (Box 18)
    - Interviews, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Names and addresses (Box 18)
    - Interview notes (Box 18)
    - Original trial transcript, volumes VI-VII (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Brief of appellee (Box 18)
    - Evidence (Box 18)
    - Discovery files (Box 19)
    - Crime scene evidence (Box 19)
    - Photos and notes (Box 19)
    - Interviews (Box 19)
    - District attorney's files, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Brown v. James French, Judge Cogburn 8/5/1996 (Box 19)
    - Brown v. James French, Judge Cogburn 8/5/1996, 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Post-conviction correspondence, 1997-1999 (Box 20)
    - Exhibits (Box 20)
    - SBI photos, crime scene before and after (Box 20)
    - Pinehurst police department, Don Davis investigation (Box 20)
    - Writ of certiorari and motion for appropriate relief (Box 21)
    - Press and appeals (Box 21)
    - Supreme Court documents and uncategorized (Box 21)
    - U.S Court of Appeals documents (Box 21)
    - Supplemental discovery, 4 folders (Box 21)
    - Supplemental discovery, 8 folders (Box 22)
    - Fourth Circuit filings, 11/21/1988; 1/17/1989; 2/17/1989 (Box 22)
    - Discovery Filings, 1991-1993; 5 folders (Box 157)
      Scope and Contents
      addition to David Jr. Brown subseries
    - Discovery Affidavits, 1969-1992; 24 folders (Box 157)
    - Notes, 1987-1994; 5 folders (Box 157)
    - Research, 1980-1994; 13 folders (Box 157)
    - Witness Statements, 1980; 41 folders (Box 158)
    - Greeting Cards, n.d.; 1 folder (Box 158)
    - Photographs, 1953-1979; 1 folder (Box 158)
    - Appeals in 4th Circuit Court, 1987-1994; 9 folders (Box 158)
    - Appeals in Western District NC, 1987-1996; 11 folders (Box 158)
    - Appeals in 4th Circuit Court, 1990-1993; 3 folders (Box 159)
    - Appeals in Western District NC, 1987-1995; 17 folders (Box 159)
    - Notes, 1994-1996; 3 folders (Box 159)
    - NC House Bill 9, 1995; 2 folders (Box 159)
    - Discovery, 1980-1994; 2 folders (Box 159)
    - Memos, 1995-1996; 1 folder (Box 159)
    - Interview Notes, 1994; 3 folders (Box 159)
    - SBI Reports, 1994; 2 folders (Box 159)
    - Subpoenas, 1980; n.d.; 2 folders (Box 159)
    - Exhibits list, n.d.; 2 folders (Box 159)
    - Motion to Unseal Envelope, 1996; 1 folder (Box 159)
    - Briefs, 1982; 2 folders (Box 159)
    - Appeal Notebook, 1976-1994; 27 folders (Box 159)
    - Direct Appeal Pleadings, 1985-1986; 2 folders (Box 160)
    - Crime Scene Photos, 1980; 1 folder (Box 160)
    - Maps, n.d.; 1 folder (Box 160)
    - Discovery Letter, 1995; 1 folder (Box 160)
    - Interview Notes, 1991-1995; 1 folder (Box 160)
    - Direct Appeal, 1982-1983; 14 folders (Box 160)
    - Trial File, 1980-1981; 8 folders (Box 160)
    - Trial File, 1980; 20 folders (Box 161)
    - Direct Appeal, 1982-1983; 2 folders (Box 161)
    - NC Supreme Court, 1981-1984; 24 folders (Box 161)
    - NC Superior Court, 1984; 1 folder (Box 161)
    - Case Law, 1986-1994; 12 folders (Box 161)
    - Petition for Writ of Certiorari, 1985-1986; 5 folders (Box 161)
    - Case Law, 1986-1994; 10 folders (Box 162)
    - Writ of Habeas Corups Western District NC, 1987-1988; 8 folders (Box 162)
    - Motion for Stay of Execution, 1988; 1 folder (Box 162)
    - Appeal Litigation, 1988; 13 folders (Box 162)
    - Appeal Litigation, 1996; 35 folders (Box 162)
      Contains floppy disc
    - Crime Scene Photos, 1980; 1 folder (Box 162)
      Images depict scene of murder, graphic gore and violence, including deceased persons
  - Frederick Camacho, 1995-1996, 2 boxes
    Fred Camacho was convicted of first-degree murder and sentenced to death in Mecklenburg County. The North Carolina Supreme Court reversed his conviction and sentence because of the failure of trial to instruct the jury on the lesser-included offense of second-degree murder. The prosecution and Camacho entered a plea bargain agreement following the reversal, resulting in a sentence less than death.
    - Statement of the facts (Box 23)
    - Exhibits, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Transcripts
      - Pretrial motions, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Hearing on motion to strike death penalty, 3 folders (Box 23)
      - Second trial guilty plea (Box 23)
    - Exhibits in support of motion to strike death penalty (Box 23)
    - Exhibits in support of motion to strike death penalty, 4 folders (Box 24)
    - Pleadings, direct appeal, 1994; 3 folders (Box 132)
  - Willie Ervin Fisher, 1980-1999, 6 boxes
    Willie Fisher was charged with the April 1992 murder of his girlfriend. Fisher's attorney did not prepare for the trial adequately and neglected mental health and social history mitigating evidence. His attorney was disbarred mid-trial and Fisher was appointed a new lawyer who did not file a brief before the court's ruling. Fisher, an African American, was sentenced to death by a jury of 11 whites and one African American and was executed on March 9, 2001.
    - U.S. Fourth Circuit Court of Appeals (Box 24)
      - Brief of appellant (Box 24)
      - Reply brief of appellant (Box 24)
      - Brief of appellee (Box 24)
      - Appendix - volume I (Box 24)
      - Appendix - volume II (Box 24)
    - Appendix - volume III (Box 25)
    - Appendix to defendant's motion for appropriate relief (Box 25)
    - Briefs (Box 25)
    - State answer to motion of appriopriate relief (Box 25)
    - Respondent's answer to writ of habeas corpus (Box 25)
    - Motion of appropriate relief (MAR) (Box 25)
    - Fisher background information (digest) (Box 25)
    - Final order (Box 25)
    - Affidavits (Box 25)
    - Petitioner response to state's motion for summary judgment (Box 25)
    - State's pre-hearing motions (Box 25)
    - Fisher's statements (Box 25)
    - Dr. Matthew, psychiatrist (Box 25)
    - Recommendation of U.S. magistrate judge (Box 25)
    - Court's order regarding attorney/client waiver (Box 25)
    - Appointment motions - federal court (Box 25)
    - Correspondence with LEX group (Box 25)
    - Federal district court judgment (Box 25)
    - Post-hearing proposed orders (Box 26)
    - Defendant response to summary judgment and motion for appropriate relief (MAR) (Box 26)
    - Writ of Certiorari (Box 26)
    - N.C. Supreme Court - briefs (Box 26)
    - Petition for clemency (Box 26)
    - Supplementary appendix to MAR
      - Volume II (Box 26)
      - Volume III (Box 26)
    - Exhibits from evidentiary hearing (Box 26)
    - Petition for rehearing (Box 26)
    - Petition for writ of certiorari matters (Box 26)
    - Fourth Circuit orders (Box 26)
    - N.C. Supreme Court orders (Box 26)
    - Appendix litigation (Box 26)
    - Abeyance motion (Box 26)
    - Tamer consent order of discipline (Box 26)